Finding Aid for John Gibson Parkhurst papers (microfilm), 1860-1909
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Gibson Parkhurst papers (microfilm) 1860-1909 1860-1865
Parkhurst, John G. (John Gibson), 1824-1906.
4 microfilm rolls
mf 419c-mf422c
Lawyer at Coldwater, Michigan, Civil War officer, U.S. Marshal of Eastern District of Michigan and Minister to Belgium. Civil War letters describing his service as Colonel of the Ninth Michigan Infantry and other units.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The Civil War papers of John G. Parkhurst were filmed in 2006. The papers from the Bentley Historical Library came from Mrs. Andrew Ness (donor no. 712 ) in 1941; and from the W. K. Foundation (donor no. 1165 )
The collection is open to research.
The originals of the Parkhust civil War material (as well as other Parkurts papers) are available at the Bentley Historical Library, Universityof Michigan and Michigan State University Archives and Historical Collection.
John G. Parkhurst was born April 17, 1824 at Oneida Castle, New York. He attended Oneida Academy, then studied law in the office of N. F. Graves. He was admitted to the bar in 1847. He moved to Coldwater, Michigan in 1849 and open up a law practice. With the outbreak of the Civil War, Governor Blair appointed Parkhurst to be lieutenant colonel of the 9th Michigan Infantry. He was taken prisoner at Murfreesboro in July 1862, spent three months in a Southern prison, and was exchanged in December 1862. He served as lieutenant colonel and colonel in the 9th Michigan Infantry, provost marshal of the 14th Army Corps and of the Military District of Tennessee, and was brevet brigadier general of U. S. Volunteers. He served under General George H. Thomas.
From 1866 to 1869 he was marshal of the Michigan District. A life-long Democrat ran for various offices, usually without success. President Cleveland rewarded his service to his party and to the nation, naming Parkhurst as Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of the United States to Belgium. He served from 1888 to 1889. In 1893, President Cleveland commissioned him postmaster of Coldwater where he served until 1897.
Parkhurst had many other interests. As early as 1849, he was engaged in the insurance business which he continued throughout his life. He also invested in farm lands and participated in veterans organizations. He died May 6, 1906.
The John G. Parkhurst microfilm collection is comprised of two series: Civil War papers from the Parkhurst collection at the Bentley Historical Library, and Civil War papers from the Parkhurst collection at Michigan State University Archives and Historical Collection. Originals of these papers are available for examination at their respective institutions.
Subjects:
Parkhurst, John G. (John Gibson), 1824-1906.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 9th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Johnson, Andrew, 1808-1875.; Photographs.; Society of the Army of the Cumberland.
- Parkhurst Civil War Papers (Bentley Historical Library)
  From 1861 to 1866, Parkhurst wrote one hundred and five letters to his sisters and to his young daughter. In these letters, he describes Fort Wayne and the steamer Mississippi; also the camp at West Point, Ky., with a drawing of the streets of tents and of his tent in particular. He writes of sickness in camp, his duties, marches, guerrillas, Vallandigham's crossing, and skirmishes with Morgan. He tells about the crops, the flies, and spring floods. He describes the beauties of the countryside, the conditions of the roads and the supply lines, and the fighting around Murfreesboro, Chattanooga and at Chickamauga, and the siege of Atlanta, with a special account of the battle of Stones River. He also tells of the forming of the 23rd Brigade, the exchange of prisoners, and mustering out. There are comments on General Thomas and a great many on his own family and personal affairs. Associated with these letters are the several files of other Civil War documents that he preserved, his recollection of the Battle of Stones River, and his involvement with veterans groups. The microfilm of these papers is available for inter-library loan.
  - Family history notes (Reel 1)
  - Letters, 1860-March 1862 (Reel 1)
  - Letters, April 1862-September 1864 (Reel 2)
  - Letters, October 1864-December 1865 (Reel 3)
  - List of prisoners of war captured by troops under command of General George H. Thomas, 1864 (Reel 3)
  - Veterans organizations and related, 1863-1909 (Reel 3)
  - Claim made by General Parkhurst for the loss of two horses in the Civil War (Reel 3)
  - List of persons indicted for treason in Tennessee during the Civil War (Reel 3)
  - Recollections of the Battle of Stones River, account dated February 6, 1890 (Reel 3)
  - Photographs (Reel 3)
- Parkhurst Civil War Collection (Michigan State University Archives and Historical Collection)
  - Correspondence, 1861-1865 (Reel 4)
  - Diaries, 1861-1865, 5 volumes (Reel 4)
  - Field orders, 1862, 1864-1865 (Reel 4)
  - Official military records, 1861-1865 (Reel 4)
  - Reunion invitations
    - 1881-1889 (Reel 4)
    - 1891-1895 and undated (Reel 4)
  - Reunion programs
    - 1868-1871 (Reel 4)
    - 1887-1888 (Reel 4)
    - 1897, 1912 (Reel 4)
  - Reports of Battles: Mill Spring and Stones River (Reel 4)
  - Roster (annotated) of the Ninth Michigan Infantry, 1861 (Reel 4)
    (published 1892)